Guide to the Thomas Holman Collection of Flatiron Building Photographs and Ephemera circa 1902-2004 (bulk, 1903-1909) PR 372
New-York Historical Society
Thomas Holman collection of Flatiron Building photographs and ephemera
circa 1902-2004 (bulk, 1903-1909)
New-York Historical Society
Holman, Thomas Seth, 1953-2015
PR 372
1.25 Linear feet (in 3 boxes and 1 oversize folder)
A small collection of visual representations of Manhattan's iconic Flatiron Building (1902), in photographs, prints, stereographs, on postcards, sheet music and magazine covers, and dining menus, assembled by art historian Thomas Holman.
Arrangement
The collection came to the New-York Historical Society in no discernible order. It has been organized alphabetically by format under the following categories:
• book
• calendar
• dining menus
• exhibition catalog
• greeting cards
• map
• periodical
• photographic negatives [GLASS]
• photographs
• postcards
• prints
• sheet music
• stereographs
• toy
• unrelated material
Historical / Biographical Note
Manhattan's iconic Flatiron Building, designed by architect Daniel H. Burnham and completed in 1902 on the triangular gore formed by the intersection of Broadway, Fifth Avenue, and 23rd Street, was originally called the Fuller Building for its original owner, the George A. Fuller Company architectural firm. Its popular, and now official, name, comes from its similarity to the shape of a cast-iron clothes iron. To some early sightseers it even resembled a ship, its prow aiming north up Fifth Avenue. The building's shape, combined with its height, causes gusty downdrafts near its "cowcatcher" at 23rd Street. This gave rise, it is believed, to the phrase "23 Skidoo," said by police officers to chase away men who lingered on the corner in hope of catching a glimpse of forbidden female stocking bared by the wind. Images of the Flatiron Building have appeared on countless advertisements, postcards, souvenirs, sheet music covers, paintings, and photographs. Even the surrounding neighborhood, the Flatiron District, bears its name. The building was designated a New York City landmark in 1966. For more, see Alice Sparberg Alexiou's 2010 book, The Flatiron: The New York Landmark and the Incomparable City That Arose With It, available at the New-York Historical Society's Patricia D. Klingenstein Library (call no. F128.8.F55 A44 2010).
Native New Yorker Thomas Seth Holman (1953–2015), assembler of the present collection, was an author, art historian, and private art advisor who held degrees from Macalester College and the University of Chicago and also studied at Oxford and the University of Vienna. Holman filled curatorial and directorial positions at the Albany Museum of Art, the Forum Gallery, the Hudson River Museum, the Marietta/Cobb Museum of Art, the Minnesota Museum of American Art, and the Norton Museum of Art. His main, personal, collecting focus was on souvenirs of the Grand Tour of the 18th and 19th centuries, when wealthy young Englishmen traveled the European continent in pursuit of the knowledge of languages, history, art, and architecture.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Thomas S. Holman in memory of Merton Holman, 2013.
Related Materials
Additional postcards of the Flatiron Building may be found in the New-York Historical Society Postcard Collection, (PR-054), box 44, and additional stereographs are located in the Stereograph File, (PR-065), box 31.
Scope and Contents
Art historian Thomas Holman collected visual representations of the Flatiron Building. Since its completion in 1902 the popularity of the skyscraper has ensured its continued appearance on advertisements, postcards, menus, sheet music covers, and greeting cards. Photographs of the building, and commercially-produced stereographic views abound. While not extensive, Holman's collection is probably strongest in its postcards (see Box 2, Folders 2-17), most of which date from the early 20th century and depict the Flatiron under construction, and, once completed, during daylight, nighttime, and snowstorms. Some cards make humorous reference to the phrase "23 Skidoo" by showing women's skirts flying on the Flatiron's windy corners.
Flatiron Building (New York, N.Y.); Calendars.; Glass negatives.; Greeting cards; Mechanical toys; Menus.; Periodicals.; Postcards.; Prints (visual works).; Sheet music.; Stereographs.; Tourist maps
- Book | Nancy Groce, New York: Songs of the City, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Reproduces several sheet music covers depicting the Flatiron Building.
- Calendar | Flatiron Building 1997 Calendar, 1996 (Oversize FF)
- Dining menus (2), 1906, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  • Flat Iron Restaurant [in Flatiron Building], Five Hundred Members Night Banquet, National Lodge No. 209, F. & A.M., Friday, April 27th, 1906
  • Flatiron Diner & Baking Company [18 West 18th Street], Preview Menu, December 1996
- Exhibition catalog | The Prowed Tower: Early Images of the Flatiron Building, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Catalog for the exhibit "The Prowed Tower: Early Images of the Flatiron Building," curated by Bruce Weber at the Berry-Hill Galleries, 11 East 70th Street, Manhattan. The exhibit ran from November 14 through December 28, 1991.
- Greeting cards (4), 1995-1999 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
  Four greeting cards (two inscribed to Thomas Holman) depicting the Flatiron Building.
- Map | Flatiron District Visitors' Guide (2), [1990s] (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Periodical | Fame: A Journal for Advertisers (vol. 36, no. 5), 1927 October (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Flatiron Building on cover.
- Periodical | Flatiron News (4 folders), 1995-1996 (Box 1, Folder 6-9)
  Five issues of the Flatiron News: vol. 1, nos. 1-3, and vol. 2, no. 5. The Flatiron Building appears on some covers, and as the letter "I" in the magazine's title.
- Periodical | Where New York, 1995 April (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Photographic negatives [GLASS] | Broadway, north to East 19th Street, 1913 November 2 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Photographic negatives [GLASS] | Broadway, north to East 23rd Street (at Flatiron Building), 1913 November 23 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Includes a print made from the glass plate.
- Photographs | Flatiron Building site (1), circa 1902 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Modern, mounted 8 x 10-inch print of a historic photograph.
- Photographs | Flatiron Building under construction (1), circa 1902 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Photographs | Flatiron Building (1), 1910 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Photographs | Flatiron Building (4), undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  Modern, mounted 8 x 10-inch prints of historic photographs.
- Photographs | "Seeing New York" tour bus at Flatiron Building (1), undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Photographs | Aerial view (1), 1930 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  Modern, mounted 8 x 10-inch print of a historic photograph. A notation on verso of the mount reads "Madison Square aerial overview [looking] south towards Union Square with U.S. Navy Planes, 1930."
- Postcards | "23 Skidoo" (5), circa 1907-1916 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 2)
  Five postcards featuring the phrase "23 Skidoo," which is thought to have originated near the prow of the Flatiron Building, at the intersection of Broadway, Fifth Avenue, and 23rd Street, where men lingered to catch sight of female ankles exposed by the downdrafts blowing off the skyscraper. Police officers, wise to what they were doing, would chase them away with a "23 Skidoo."
- Postcards | Flatiron Building alone (35), circa 1903-1913 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 3)
- Postcards | Flatiron Building and vicinity (14), circa 1904-1909 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 4)
- Postcards | Flatiron Building foldout (2), circa 1905 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 5)
  Two wooden or paper-board postcards of the Flatiron Building, with center panels that pull out to reveal other New York City sights.
- Postcards | Flatiron Building holiday and souvenir greetings (8), circa 1904-1912 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 6)
- Postcards | Flatiron Building humorous (4), 1907, 1908, 1992 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 7)
- Postcards | Flatiron Building lenticular printing (1), 1903 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 8)
  A lenticular printed postcard that, when tilted left or right, displays alternate views of the Flatiron Building and the structures it replaced.
- Postcards | Flatiron Building modern (6), 1980s-1990s (Offsite-box 2, Folder 9)
- Postcards | Flatiron Building night views (10), circa 1905-1909 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 10)
- Postcards | Flatiron Building real photo (3), circa 1904-1920s (Offsite-box 2, Folder 11)
- Postcards | Flatiron Building romantic (7), circa 1907-1909 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 12)
  Views depicting male-female couples strolling near the Flatiron Building, or dropping letters into a mailbox near the skyscraper.
- Postcards | Flatiron Building under construction (2), circa 1907 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 13)
  Note that the date of circa 1907 refers to the approximate year these cards were published, not the construction of the Flatiron Building, which was completed in 1902.
- Postcards | Flatiron Building windy corner (6), circa 1902-1909 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 14)
  Humorous views depicting hats, umbrellas, and skirts flying in the downdrafts of the Flatiron Building.
- Postcards | Flatiron Building winter scenes (2), 1906, 1908 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 15)
- Postcards | Seeing New York, 1904-1907 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 16)
  Two postcards and an advertisement for the American Sight-Seeing Car and Coach Company's "Seeing New York" tour bus, which operated from the Flatiron Building.
- Postcards | New York Skyscrapers Souvenir Folder, circa 1913 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 17)
  Includes a view of the Flatiron Building.
- Prints (2), 1902 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  Two printed images of the Flatiron Building after a 1902 photograph by C. L. Ritzmann that were apparently cut from periodicals.
- Sheet music | Don't Blame it All on Broadway, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  Front cover depicting the Flatiron Building, and first page of the song by Bert Grant to lyrics by Harry Williams and Joe Young.
- Stereographs (3), 1904-1925 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 18)
  • A.C. Co., 1925 | 33. "Flat Iron Building, New York City."
  • Geo. W. Griffith, n.d. | 2783. Flatiron Building and Fifth Avenue, New York, N.Y.
  • International Stereograph Co., 1904 | 21606. "The Celebrated "Flat Iron" Building, Broadway and Fifth Avenue, New York City, U.S.A."
- Stereographs (4), 1903-1904 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 19)
  • Keystone View Company, 1903 | 13504. "Flat iron" Building, Fifth Avenue and Broadway, New York, N.Y., U.S.A.
  • Keystone View Company, n.d. | 13504. "The Flatiron Building, Fifth Avenue and Broadway, New York, N.Y."
  • Keystone View Company, n.d. | V23215. "Flatiron Building (S), Most Remarkable Business Structure on Earth, New York, N.Y."
  • Keystone View Company, 1904 | 13772. "Up Broadway and Fifth Avenue from Flat Iron Building, New York, N.Y., U.S.A."
- Stereographs (2), 1903-1904 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 20)
  • "Perfec" Stereograph, 1903 | 10. "Most striking of Sky-scrapers,—the "Flatiron" Bldg., (20 Stories) Broadway, New York, U.S.A.
  • William H. Rau, 1904 | "New York's Celebrated Flatiron (Fuller) Building, Intersection of Broadway and 5th Ave. (20 Stories, 286 Ft. High).
- Stereographs (2), 1903-1904 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 21)
  • Underwood & Underwood, 1903 | 99. "The Famous Flatiron Building—most remarkable commercial building in the World, New York"
  • Underwood & Underwood, 1904 | (99)-5316. "The famous Flatiron Building—most remarkable commercial building in the world, New York"
- Stereographs (1), undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 22)
  • No publisher, n.d. | "Flat Iron Building and View of Fifth Avenue."
- Toy | Car with "23 Skidoo" slogan, [1930s?] (Offsite-box 3)
  Red tin toy convertible coupe jalopy by Linemar toys, the Japanese-manufactured division of Louis Marx and Company, covered with slogans like "10 Miles to a Gal," "Sit Here and Be on Top," "Dig This Crazy Car," and "23 Skidoo."
- Unrelated material | map, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  Larry Wolfe Horwitz's Official Map of Movie Stars' Homes, New York City
- Unrelated material | poster, 1997 (Oversize FF)
  Poster announcing the route of "Disney's Hercules Electrical Parade / Midtown Manhattan / Saturday, June 14, 1997 / 9 pm to 11 pm."
- Unrelated material | transit ephemera, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  Six copies of an MTA / New York City Transit leaflet outlining subway entrance restrictions at Penn Station, street closures, and bus reroutings during the 2004 Republican National Convention, held at Madison Square Garden, August 30 through September 2.